ENG.MOHAMMAD HAZAZI

IT Director | GRC, OEX, PMO, CGEIT, PMP, RMP, ITIL

mhazazi@pm.me

+966 53 7080709

Linkedin | Mhazazi

Riyadh, SA

ABOUT ME

Creativity & passion is a part of who I am! I seek to find ways to adapt when needed and disrupt when possible.

For the past 15 years, I have been at the forefront of digital evolution and transformation as an intrepid IT professional with broad-based experience in IT Solution Engineering, Project Management, Enterprise Architecture, IT Auditing, Customer Experience, and Governance & Operational Excellence! Which have enabled businesses and enterprises to perform at their optimal level and to realize their business objectives.

In a nutshell, together, we shall transform your business through the power of people, processes, technology, and innovation.

AREA OF EXPERTISE

- Thinking through 1st principles
- Mentorship and team building
- Governance Frameworks
- Enterprise Architecture
- Change Management
- Business Continuity & Resiliency
- Digital Transformation
- Customer Experience
- Project Management
- PMO Establishment
- Innovation & Continuous Improvement
- IT Demand Management
- IT Strategy & Blueprint
- IT Audit & RM
- Operational Excellence

WORK EXPERIENCE



Ministry of Health

(1Year, 2 Mos)

Riyadh First Health Cluster

Director of IT Governance & Portfolio Management

Jul 2022 - Present

- Spearheaded the development of the Digital Health strategy to guide and govern digital innovation and support internal partners to ensure programs and strategies are implemented and maintained effectively.
- Discuss and approve overall digital architecture strategy & direction and oversee the implementation of new digital Innovation initiatives across the cluster.
- Manage the overall delivery planning and execution of 500M+ digital portfolios based on industry-leading best practices. This includes collaborating with other senior management teammates to discuss project schedules and plans, risks, issues, dependencies, and corrective actions.
- Manage implementing new technology initiatives, streamlining, automating, and simplifying business processes, and upskilling staff across the organization to use the technologies and processes effectively.
- Formalized organization-wide IT demand, portfolio management, and streamlined shared services for IT to enable standardized IT Services and capabilities while optimizing operational efficiency.
- Overseeing IT governance framework within the organization to ensure IT is aligned with the organization's overall business goals and objectives and that business continuity and IT risks are managed effectively
- Designed and implemented IT Governance models & Policies, IT Processes, Guidelines and Performance Management framework.
- Defined and monitored the overall direction of data management capabilities. Worked on improving data quality, increasing data literacy, and maximizing data use in achieving organizational goals.
- Led a joint IT audit with the General Court of Audit to review IT spending, capital O&M contracts, and fixed assets. Ensured that resources were properly used and IT complied with financial, digital, and administrative regulations.
- Developed and implemented a new IT audit framework that improved the efficiency and effectiveness of the audit function and successfully communicated audit findings to the board committee and stakeholders, resulting in the implementation of corrective actions.
- Architecting the Operational Excellence program to help the organization achieve and sustain excellence by raising performance standards by continuously improving IT's business processes, systems, and policies.

King Saud Medical City

Director of Governance & Operational Excellence

Jul 2022 - Present

- Led the implementation of the Digital Transformation Measurements to help the organization provide innovative and creative IT services, ensure effective digital transformation, and boost its strength to maintain sustainability and define improvement opportunities.
- Direct the development of IT policies, processes, and procedures to ensure consistent application and ease of operations for IT departments.
- Oversee management of IT Service business continuity and change management activities and collaborate with information Security on mutual security projects, programs, and plans.

Head of IT PMO

Jul 2022 - Present

- Managing +200M SR IT Portfolios, with more than 17 Programs and 40+ Projects varying from CX to Core Applications, to Digital Data, Integration, and Security to Modernize IT infrastructures and Governance.
- Managing customer demand analysis and study to produce a detailed project proposal package and concur with stakeholders to secure the necessary fund and develop the RFP & Tender documents.
- Adopted a new Project Information Management system to track all IT portfolios, programs, and projects while achieving team synergy and maintaining information consistency and visibility for main stakeholders.
- Introduced and develop a new IT PMO operating model and worked with the team to sustain operational excellence within PMO through upskilling training sessions to increase team efficiency in managing and monitoring assigned projects.

Senior IT Project Manager

Jun 2022 - Jun 2022

 Spearheaded KSMC Digital Transformation Projects (Application & Infrastructure). And Revamp IT PMO toward modern and value-centric PMO by aligning project goals with business objectives, maximizing resource utilization, and helping overcome IT market volatility challenges.



Boston Consulting Group, Remote

(3Mos)

Junior Consultant

Jan 2023 - Mar 2023

- Mentored by BCG to provide expert-level insight on Conducting business analysis and research to identify critical metrics and opportunities for improvement.
- Conducted a feasibility study, Market study & research, and Analyses of Customer Requirements.
- Developed processes and procedures to ensure business solutions meet strategic goals.



Aramco, Riyadh-KSA

(7Yrs 5Mos)

IT Project Manager

Jan 2020 - May 2022

- Led IT mega project at King Abdullah financial district by providing IT requirements specifications, reviewing the
 3rd parity detailed design, and supervising the implementation stage.
- Led and managed IT Customer Engagement project to explore opportunities for End-user Devices optimization & financial saving, promote the utilization of newly released IT services, address customer concerns, and provide a positive user experience.
- Led and managed IT Asset & infrastructure Optimization projects to leverage IT asset utilization for the maximum business advantage by reducing additional operational costs.
- Led and managed the operational excellence project to foster the innovation culture and Motivate employees to generate ideas, emphasize the importance of acting upon opportunities, and develop financial saving revenues exceeding 20M\$.
- Supported and Coordinated IT projects by reviewing Engineering design packages, Scope of Works, Factory Acceptance Test (FAT), Site Acceptance Test (SAT), commissioning activities, and Mechanical Completion Certificate (MCC) walkthrough.

IT Service Management

Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

- Directed regional IT service management team to strengthen the customer experience of IT services and ensure continual service improvement.
- Led and supported service induction efforts to engage interactively with customers, orchestrate awareness and marketing on customer-facing IT services to provide better knowledge and boost IT services utilization.
- Acted as liaison with the Portfolio Management team to build, develop, and nurture relationships with Crosse functional organization's leaders and SMEs to be able to diagnose existing and foreseen business challenges and recommend IT solutions to improve the situation.

IT Infrastructure O&M

Jan 2015 - Dec 2018

- Managed & supported strategic IT initiatives to optimize infrastructure efficiency and improve customer experience, resulting in 5M\$ cost savings & avoidance.
- Led and supervised the operation and maintenance of unified communications systems in the central province to maintain 99% of service availability & reliability.
- Served as IT SME to review project proposals and detailed designs of communication infrastructure and data network engineering designs, including radio, satellite, telephony, video, and unified communications.
- Ensured IT alignment with business demand to provide maximum value for Aramco. I also managed the development of communications and maintenance of IT business continuity plans.
- Coached 10 Summer interns in the completion of field activities and maintenance operation tasks.



Presidio, Houston-USA

(1Yr)

Network Engineer

Jan 2014 - Dec 2014

 Participated with functional teams on scoping, designing, and implementing Network, Collaboration, Application, and Enterprise Mobility projects for Cisco.



Aramco, Riyadh-KSA

(4Yrs 2Mos)

IT Backbone Support

Oct 2009 - Dec 2013

Handled the responsibility of repairing, installing, modifying, and upgrading telecommunications and data network systems and related equipment.



BTC Networks, Riyadh-KSA

(2Yrs)

Telecom Technician

Sep 2007 - Sep 2009

 Installing and troubleshooting Leased Lines, SHDSL, ADSL, E1, DDN, Transmission Circuit, and Gigabit Ethernet to support STC operations.

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATION & LEADERSHIP TRAINING

Professional:

• The Open Group: TOGAF -Planned Sep 2023-

• ISACA: CGEIT -in progress-

PMI: PMP, RMPAXELOS: ITIL 4

HP: ATP Flex Network

• CISCO: CCENT, CCNA R&S, CCNA SEC, CCNP SEC

Leadership:

- Executive Leadership, Columbia Business School
- Personal Leadership and Success Program, The Tuck School of Business at Dartmouth
- Innovation & Creativity, Harvard Business School
- PMO for Management Consultants, Aramco
- Customer-Centric IT Strategy, Aramco

EDUCATION

(BS) Information Technology (AD) Telecommunication

Saudi Electronic University – KSA College of Telecom & Electronics - KSA

Attributes & Competencies

- Motivational Leader
- Business Acumen
- Lifelong Lerner
- Public Speaker
- Visionary

- Fusing business & technology
- Digitizing the Enterprise
- Leveraging ecosystem
- Shaping innovation
- Driving Agility

- Time & Conflict Management
- Persuasion & Influence
- Risk Optimization
- Problem-Solving
- Unlock Potentials